"The Benefits of Gum Chewing
for Halitosis (Bad Breath)"
What is the impact of chewing
gum on bad breath?
In the Journal of Evidence-Based
Dental Practice,
a study compared the levels
of stinky breath compounds
in people’s mouths before and after
chewing mint gum for 15 minutes,
and they found that chewing gum
significantly decreased
the levels of all the volatile
sulfur compounds they tested,
reducing them all by about half,
which they attribute to the effect
that chewing gum
has on salivation.
How do we know the mint didn’t
have anything to do with it?
Because flavorless chewing gum
base without any active ingredient
can work too; so, chewing gum
may indeed control bad breath
temporarily because it triggers
the salivary flow.
That’s thought to be why we wake
up with morning breath,
but it just goes
away on its own
even if you don’t brush
your teeth or anything.
Here’s the levels of the stinky
volatile sulfur compounds
in people’s breath right
when they wake up,
dropping even before
they eat breakfast.
That’s because we have 1 1/2 liters
—that’s like 6 cups—
of saliva bathing
down our tongue daily,
but the spigot
is turned down at night
and bacteria grow
in the stagnant puddle
that is your nighttime mouth.
Saliva works because of the simple
fact that larger saliva volumes
allow increased amounts of volatile
sulfur compounds to enter solution.
Instead of off-gassing,
the gases dissolve in the fluid.
This can also be accomplished
by just drinking some water
or by using chewing gum since
that causes your mouth to water.
Is there any flavor we can add
that makes it work better?
A study on eucalyptus-flavored
chewing gum was published.
People were randomized to chew
a high-concentration eucalyptus gum
5 times a day,
a low-concentration gum,
or just a flavorless gum.
And both of the eucalyptus-flavored
gums significantly beat out
the control group gum, both
quantitatively and koala-tatively.
OK, but where are you going
to find eucalyptus gum?
What about the effect
of cinnamon?
Against one bad
breath-associated bacteria,
cinnamon oil kicked tush,
suggesting it’s a promising
substance to incorporate
into oral hygiene products
for controlling bad breath,
but it utterly failed to control
four other types
of bad breath bacteria.
These studies were all just
done in petri dishes, though.
You don’t really know
if cinnamon-flavored gum
would help with bad breath
until...you put it to the test.
The short-term
germ-killing effect
of sugar-sweetened
cinnamon chewing gum
on bacteria associated
with bad breath and…
the researchers conclude
that commercially available
sugar-sweetened
cinnamon chewing gum
may indeed benefit bad breath,
but if you look at the
actual data,
the same gum without
cinnamon oil did no different
than the gum
with cinnamon oil.
Why were they so eager
to spin the results
to suggest some sort
of unique benefit?
Perhaps because the study
was funded by Wrigley.
Bottomline, gum chewing per se
is considered to be helpful
in reducing bad breath
by stimulating saliva flow
and mechanical cleansing,
even if there’s no “active”
ingredients in it.